<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King, a proclamation. James R. Whereas we are certainly informed that our unnatural enemy, the Prince of Orange, doth intend suddenly to invade this our kingdom of Ireland, ...</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1685-1688 : James II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B25065</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99886381</idno>
  <idno type="VID">186639</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264215102</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing J285</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.21.f.12[67]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide G.6022[71]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R225922</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99886381</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99886381e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B25065)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 186639)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C5:2[67]; C23:1[71])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King, a proclamation. James R. Whereas we are certainly informed that our unnatural enemy, the Prince of Orange, doth intend suddenly to invade this our kingdom of Ireland, ...</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1685-1688 : James II)</author>
                  <author>James II, King of England, 1633-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Andrew Crook and Samuel Helsham, assigns of Benjamin Tooke printer to the King's most excellent Majesty; and are to be sold at his Majesties printing-house on Ormonde-Key, and the Colledge-Arms in Castle-street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from caption title and opening lines of text.</note>
                  <note>"Given at our court at our castle of Dublin, the 5th day of August 1689."</note>
                  <note>Summoning all Roman Catholics to the standard. Cf. Steele.</note>
                  <note>Arms 186.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Ireland --  History --  War of 1689-1691 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:186639:1"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal coat of arms of England</figDesc>
                  <p>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</p>
                  <p>DIEV ET MON DROIT</p>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>By The KING,</head>
            <head>A PROCLAMATION.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>JAMES R.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEREAS We are certainly informed that Our unnatural Enemy, the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend suddenly to invade this Our Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> having an Army of Forreigners and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels ready to land in one or more places thereof; and that for the better compassing of his unjust ends therein, and for the better encouragement of the said Forreigners and Rebels in so great an undertaking, the said Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised to bestow and distribute all the Lands of <hi>Ireland</hi> belonging to all Our Catholicks, and other Our Loyal Subjects here, amongst the said <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eigners and Rebels, and to confer upon them all the Offices, whether <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> or Military, Ecclesiastical or Temporal, within this Realm, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to extirpate, ruine and destroy all Our Catholicks, and other Our Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Subjects within this Our Kingdom. For the prevention whereof, We have heretofore summoned all Our Roman Catholick Subjects, from sixteen to sixty, to be ready, as well armed as they can, to oppose the said Invaders. And to the same purpose We have ordered a Militia to be settled in Our seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Counties of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and have also commanded certain Forces to be raised for the recruiting Our Standing Army. And whereas several Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains with great chearfulness, out of their fervent zeal to Vs, have raised several Companies for Our Service, and subsisted them for many months at their own Costs and Charges; some whereof were Regimented under certain Collonels, and others of them were independent Companies, not inlisted in any Regiment: And though We were very sensible of their zealous carriage towards Vs, yet, as well to lessen the charge We were at in supporting
<pb facs="tcp:186639:2"/> Our Troops, as that the circumstances of Our affairs did not require so great an Army as was then on Foot, We gave Orders that the said several Companies should be layd by from Our then present Service▪ and at the same time ordered that Our thainks should be given them, with an assurance to the said Captains that they should not only be recompenced in due time for their charges, but that they and their said Companies upon the first occasion should be imployed in Our Service, and Mustred in Our Troops, and being resolved to make a Vigorous Defence, against the unjust designes of such Forraigners and Rebels, and having to that purpose set up Our Royal Standard at Our Camp at <hi>Dublin,</hi> and knowing it to be of great Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to Our affairs, that the said Companies so layd by for a time should be made up, and that such of Our Subjects as are provided with Horses, should Immediately come to Our Assistance; We have thought fit by the advice of Our Privy Council to Charge and Require, and We do hereby strictly Charge and Require all such Captains, Inferior Officers and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers who were so layed by, and who are not now of Our Standing Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that they do forthwith get together, and that such Captaines do forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Compleat their respective Companies, and having so don, that they Immediately do Repair to Our Camp at <hi>Dublin,</hi> or to any other Place where Our Forces shall be Encamped, where they shall be out of hand put in Actual Pay, hereby requiring them to come as well Armed as they can; And We do further by the Advice aforesaid, strictly charge and require all Gentlemen and others of the Roman Catholicks of <hi>Ireland,</hi> (not being of Our Standing Army, or Officers who are to make up their Companies as aforesaid, and not being Lieutenants, Deputy Lieutenants or Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Array appointed in any County) and who are furnished with Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable Horses, that they forthwith upon their Allegiance and duty to Vs, repair to Our Royal Standard wherever the same is or shall be, and that they take special care to come as well Armed as they can, to serve Vs, as Volentiers for the defence of the Kingdom, against the Attempts of the said Forraigners and Rebels hereby Declaring that such of them as shall not be able to Subsist themselves, will be Subsisted and suplyed by Vs,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Given at Our Court at Our Castle of <hi>Dublin,</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the 5th day of <hi>August</hi>
                     </hi> 1689. <hi>And in the fifth year of Our Reign.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <hi>GOD SAVE THE KING.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>DƲBLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>Andrew Crook</hi> and <hi>Samuel Helsham,</hi> Assigns of <hi>Benjamin Tooke</hi> Printer to the King's most Excellent Majesty; and are to be Sold at His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties Printing-House on <hi>Ormond-Key,</hi> and the <hi>Colledg-Arms</hi> in <hi>Castle-street.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>